Hello everybody, thanks for watching this presentation.
This presentation covers the topics for chapter 4, but with a lot of extra detail about how
to write numerically precise code in the context that come up in deep learning.
For people who are watching this on the book website, you should understand that I'm going
to be taking live questions from AI with the best audience members periodically, and I'll
read the questions as I answer them.
So I'm going to start out by looking at the slides, but I'm going to tab back and forth
periodically to check for questions from the audience.
So go ahead and ask questions as they come up, and I'll try to answer them quickly.
Today's topic is numerical computation for deep learning.
Basic idea of numerical computation is that we need to be very careful about the way that
we handle real numbers in a few different contexts.
One is if we use an algorithm that has to do some kind of, you know, careful representation
of real numbers with a finite number of bits.
Real numbers like pi have infinitely many digits, and then when we represent them in
a computer, we usually use 32-bit floating point numbers as an approximation for real
numbers when we implement a deep learning algorithm on GPU.
The use of 32 bits to represent something that really has infinitely many digits cannot
often cause errors, and we'd like to try to minimize the amount of damage to our program
that happens when we use that representation.
Another consideration for numerical computation is how sensitive a function is to very small
changes in its input.
This comes up even if we were able to theoretically use real numbers without having to represent
them in 32 bits.
When we do things like optimize a function, if that function is very sensitive to little
tiny changes in the input, it becomes a lot harder to search for the inputs that minimize
that function because little tiny changes in our search can strongly influence the outcome
of the search.
As a brief roadmap for today, I'm going to cover two different topics.
The first is iterative optimization, how we actually make algorithms that search for the
minimal point of some function, and how this gets affected by numerical considerations.
Next, I'm going to talk about rounding error underflow and overflow, how the use of 32
bits to represent real numbers can affect deep learning programs.
Starting out with iterative optimization.
We're going to cover three different topics here.
The first is how the gradient descent algorithm works.
The second is curvature, the idea that the functions we're optimizing are nonlinear,
and how the second order curvature of these functions affects the optimization process.
And then finally, we'll have a few comments on constrained optimization.
The basic algorithm that we use for most iterative optimization is gradient descent.
And I've illustrated this here with a really simple function, f of x equals one half x
squared.
You can see it plotted with the dashed blue line that I'm highlighting with my mouse cursor.
If we would like to minimize this function, we can do it by following the gradient.
Let's say that x is greater than zero.
The gradient in this case, because the function is one dimensional, is just the derivative.
So the derivative can be represented by the value f prime of x.
Over here, f prime of x, represented by the green line, is positive.
So if we descend the gradient by moving in the opposite direction of the derivative,
everywhere that we're over here where the green line is positive, gradient descent will
move left and downhill.
So starting here, we would trace the blue curve leftward until we reach its minimum
point here.
Where the derivative is zero, we are no longer told by the derivative to move in any particular
direction.
So we stop.
If we started over here on the left side, over here, the derivative is negative.
And we move in opposite the direction of the derivative.
So we would actually apply positive updates to our input x.
And we move rightward along the function x squared until we reach the minimum and stop
where the derivative is equal to zero.
I've described gradient descent basically in terms of this idea that we move downhill
until we find a point where the derivative is zero.
In the example of f of x equals 1 half x squared, there was only one point like that.
In reality, there might be a lot of different points that have zero derivatives.
Here I've drawn a function that's very squiggly and has several different local minima.
Local minima are points that are smaller in f of x value than all of the other points
surrounding them, but they're not necessarily the lowest point overall.
So here if we look to the left or the right of this point, we go uphill a little bit.
If you go further to the left, we can find much lower points.
Usually in the context of deep learning, we can't really expect to find this global minimum
over here.
We might want to do that, but it's probably not feasible.
In practice, we often give up and find a point more like this one here.
It's a local minimum, but the value of f of x is actually very low.
So we've done a good job of reducing the value of the function, even if we don't find our
way all the way to the bottom of the function.
In practice, we don't even necessarily find a local minimum.
In practice, we often just sort of get stuck for numerical reasons, and that's the topic
of this chapter.
I'm fast-forwarding a little bit, and I'm showing you a figure from chapter 8.
On the x-axis, I show you how long gradient descent has been running on a particular problem.
In the two different plots, I show you two different things.
On the left side, I show you how big the gradients are over time, specifically, I'm plotting
the norm of the gradient.
Every little black dot is a different step of the gradient descent algorithm.
So you can see it's kind of noisy on different steps.
It's not like we always see the same gradient norm twice in a row.
It bounces around a lot, but I've fit a smooth blue curve to these lines.
You can see how the gradient norm actually gradually gets bigger over time.
Based on the plots that I showed you on the previous slides, you might expect that the
gradient norm would shrink as you approach a local minimum, and it can register go down
to zero.
Well, it turns out that a lot of the time, we actually just get stuck and can't really
keep making progress toward regions of smaller gradient norm, and so we stop when f of x
has become very small, rather than when the gradient has gone away.
You could say maybe this plot that I made here, where I show the gradient getting bigger
over time, maybe that's an example of failure.
Maybe the algorithm is just broken, but actually, if you look at the plot on the right, I'm
showing you the error rate of a classifier that we're training with gradient descent,
and this error rate decreases over time successfully and levels off to about state-of-the-art
accuracy for the problem that this is training on.
So you can see that this is actually an example of the optimization algorithm succeeding from
our point of view.
It's not actually finding a local minimum, it's just finding a very low value of the
function f of x that we're minimizing, and that low value turns out to be good enough
for us to use the model.
Someone has asked, why don't we test a larger diversity when we reach the local minimum?
Wouldn't that tell us we could go lower elsewhere?
And the answer is yes, a lot of the time we do things like run multiple random restarts
of the optimization algorithm, and sometimes you can find lower values that way.
For a lot of problems, you also find that several different random restarts end up with
about the same final value.
Someone else asked, can you please explain gradient norm a bit?
The basic idea is if you have an input to your function x with multiple coordinates,
then the gradient gives you the derivative of your function with respect to each of those
coordinates, and that tells us the direction we should go in to move downhill.
If you measure the norm of that gradient, that gives you an idea of how steep the function
is.
It tells you how quickly you can expect the function to drop if you move in a specific
direction.
I'm going to skip the next question because it's answered later in the talk, and then
there's one more question about how can the gradient increase when you are using a descent
direction?
Is it not convex?
And it turns out that the gradient can increase if you optimize a neural net because the function
is not convex.
It's also possible that if you use too large of a step size, the gradient can increase
because you move to a region that's steeper.
I think of the way that we optimize deep learning functions as more of a way of life
than a strictly mathematical discipline right now.
If you approach optimization from a really pure math point of view, you're usually looking
to do something like find literally the smallest value of some function f of x.
Or you might have some other formally defined criterion, like you're looking for a critical
point of f of x, where the value is locally the smallest in some neighborhood.
For deep learning, we usually have a more qualitative pragmatic approach, where our
goal is to just decrease the value of f of x a lot.
And we aren't necessarily hoping to actually find even a local minimum.
We just want to make the error rate go down until the error rate is low enough that our
model can be used for some engineering application.
Actually finding a critical point might be very difficult, and a lot of the critical
points that we find may not be what we want.
The next topic in our overview of iterative optimization is the effective curvature on
these optimization algorithms.
We've mentioned that gradient descent in theory will approach a critical point where the
gradient is equal to zero.
Here I show you three different kinds of critical points in one dimension.
There can be a minimum where the function curves upward around the critical point, and
the critical point is thus lower in value than all of the surrounding points.
There can also be a local maximum where the function curves downward, so the critical
point is higher in value than all the surrounding points.
Or you can have saddle points where you actually are neither a minimum nor a maximum.
Saddle points make a little bit more sense in two dimensions.
You can think of it as there's one axis where the critical point is a local minimum, and
another axis where the critical point is a local maximum.
Local maximum are usually not much of a problem for optimization algorithms.
Saddle points can be a problem for iterative optimization algorithms.
There's one algorithm called Newton's method, where the basic strategy is to solve for a
point where the gradient is equal to zero.
If you're able to solve that problem algebraically, you can jump to a solution right away.
Unfortunately, a solution in terms of Newton's method is not always actually a minimum.
If you have a function that has saddle points in it, these are also places where the gradient
is zero, but they are not really minima because they're maxima across some axes.
So algorithms like Newton's method will accidentally teleport onto saddle points and get stuck.
It turns out that for neural networks, there are a lot more saddle points than local minima.
Fortunately, saddle points are not a big problem for gradient descent.
Unless you initialize directly on the saddle point, gradient descent can escape the saddle
point.
If you look at appendix C of a paper called Qualitatively Characterizing Neural Network
Optimization Problems, I have some math there where I show why gradient descent is able
to escape.
We can characterize all of these different critical points by using curvature.
As I said, a local minimum is where the function curves up around the point and a local maximum
is where it curves down.
We can also think of this as a way of predicting how well gradient descent will perform.
Gradient descent basically says we're going to look at the slope of the function and we're
going to pretend the function is linear nearby our current x value.
And then we're going to move in a direction that will make our linear approximation go
downhill.
The amount of actual payoff that you get from that depends on how curved the function is.
If your function is perfectly linear, if you make a linear approximation to the function,
then it will just overlay the function exactly.
So here you can see I've got this dashed green line overlaying the blue line.
If we take a little step according to the direction of the derivative, we're going to
decrease the function f of x by exactly the same amount that our linear function predicted.
And that means that these iterative search algorithms, where we always just take little
steps moving downhill, are going to work really well regardless of the size of step that we
use.
If we have negative curvature, where the function curves downward as we move away from the current
point, then we're actually in a very nice situation where if we take a step that was
predicted to reduce the dashed green linear function approximating f of x, we'll find
that f of x actually decreases even more than our approximation predicted it to do.
So if we can find directions of negative curvature, they're a good way to reduce the value of
the function very quickly.
Unfortunately, what happens a lot more often is we have directions of positive curvature.
With directions of positive curvature, the function curves up relative to the linear
function.
With these small steps, we end up not nearly decreasing the function as much as we wanted
to.
In fact, if we take too big of a step, we can accidentally increase the function value.
We can overshoot the minimum in this direction and go back uphill.
That's where we start looking at what's called the numerics of the function.
We look at how much curvature there is to this function and see how it affects our
ability to take large steps to search for the minimum value of the function.
Someone asked what was the name of the paper that I just told.
You can actually see that in the slides.
They're available at deeplearningbook.org.
So far, I've shown you these one-dimensional examples of curvature.
But in practice, x is an n-dimensional vector.
And we need to understand how the curvature affects the function in many different directions.
We can do that using the Hessian matrix.
The Hessian matrix is a matrix containing all of the second derivatives.
If you look at row i and column j of the Hessian matrix, you'll find the derivative where
first we take the derivative with respect to xi, and next we take the derivative with
respect to xj.
It turns out that you can use the Hessian matrix to compute the second derivative in
a particular direction, d.
You can do that by computing d transpose hd, where d is a unit vector describing the direction
where you would like to get the second derivative.
And it turns out that there's actually some nice intuition for what second derivative
you'll get.
Hessian matrices are usually symmetric, assuming that different properties of the function
are held.
And a symmetric real-valued matrix has an eigen decomposition in terms of orthogonal
eigenvectors and eigenvalues associated with each eigenvector.
So you can write all of the eigenvectors in a matrix q, and they become this orthogonal
basis for the space that you're in.
And then you have a diagonal matrix of eigenvalues.
If we look back at some of the slides from chapter two, we can see what happens when
we multiply by a matrix that has particular eigenvectors and eigenvalues.
If we start out with a bunch of points that are represented by this blue circle here and
we multiply each of these points by a matrix that has eigenvectors v1 and v2, we'll see
that each of the points gets stretched away from the origin according to the eigenvalues
of the matrix.
So if you have a large lambda one eigenvalue associated with v1, you'll actually stretch
out the circle in this direction.
Points will get pulled further out by a factor of lambda one.
And then if you have a small eigenvalue associated with direction v2, points will get pulled
inward.
So you can see that these directions will be, when you multiply h by d, d will either
get stretched or shrunk according to how big or small the eigenvalues of the Hessian
are in that direction.
And then when you take the dot product with the direction, again, you'll end up just measuring
the size of that vector.
So you'll end up saying that the second derivative is based on how much the Hessian shrinks
or stretches your vector in that particular direction.
But what happens if your direction is not an eigenvector?
Well then it turns out that you basically interpolate based on the eigenvectors that
are nearby.
You can compute the second derivative as a sum over all the different eigenvalues.
And you multiply by this term that measures how similar the direction you're looking in
is to that corresponding eigenvalue.
You can kind of see that in this plot, that if you have a direction that's very closely
aligned with eigenvector two, you're going to get your direction stretched by approximately
eigenvalue two.
And then as you move towards eigenvalue one, the amount that your direction gets stretched
is going to scale gradually up to the amount of stretching that comes from eigenvalue one.
You're never going to stretch more than the maximum eigenvalue.
You're never going to stretch less than the minimum eigenvalue.
We can use these eigenvalues to figure out what the optimal step size is likely to be.
So first off, if we have a direction of negative curvature, even a second order approximation
would tell us that we can keep stepping forever.
That's probably not going to be true for a neural net because it's very nonlinear, it's
not even really quadratic.
It's likely to start going back uphill at some point for a large step size.
The main place where the Hessian tells us a lot of information is if we look at the
case of positive curvature, we know that if we start following the linear function downhill,
we can decrease the value of the function.
But if we step too far, we'll start to go back uphill.
We don't want to step any further than this minimum point here.
We can make a second order Taylor series approximation to the value that we'll get when we take a
specific gradient step.
We can say we're starting off at some point x0, and we're taking a gradient descent step
where we move by step size epsilon multiplied by a gradient g.
The second order Taylor series approximation tells us that the value at this new point
will be approximately equal to the value at our current point minus epsilon times the
squared norm of the gradient.
This is the first order Taylor series term, plus one half epsilon squared times the gradient
multiplied by the Hessian multiplied by the gradient.
This here is the directional second derivative in the direction of the gradient, but also
scaled by the size of the gradient.
So if we then solve this equation for the minimum predicted value that we'll get after
the step, and we solve it in terms of the step size, assuming that we're looking in
a direction of positive curvature, we find that the optimal step size is equal to the
squared norm of the gradient divided by g transpose hg.
So what does this tell us overall?
The numerator says that if the gradient is bigger, we can take bigger steps.
So big gradients will speed up the optimization algorithm.
In the denominator, we actually see that this g transpose hg term can shrink the optimal
step size a lot.
So if the gradient happens to point in a direction that's aligned with an eigenvector of the
Hessian that has a big eigenvalue, you have to slow down a lot.
Otherwise we'll overshoot the minimum and go back uphill.
Overall this shows us something about why when we actually run an iterative search in
practice, we may not actually arrive at a critical point.
Over time, we'd expect the gradient to get smaller and smaller, but we'll often also
find for the kinds of optimization problems that come up with neural nets, we'll find
that this g transpose hg term gets very big, and we're just not able to make very big steps
anymore, even if the gradient remains large.
We can measure this with something called the condition number.
The condition number looks at the largest ratio we can find between two of our eigenvalues.
If there's a very large eigenvalue and a very small eigenvalue, it means that when our gradient
points in the direction of the large eigenvalue, we're forced to take very small steps.
And we have to do that even if sometimes the gradient would point in the direction of a
small eigenvalue, and it would be safe to take larger steps.
Basically, if there's a wide range of eigenvalues, gradient descent has to miss out on a lot
of the potential value that it could find on each step.
It has to keep the step size small to avoid accidentally going up.
You can see this with this contour plot.
Here we're minimizing a quadratic function.
Each of the black rings shows a set of points where the function is of equal value.
So at the middle here, we've got a minimum of the function.
Every time we see a ring on our way out, we're taking a step up in value of the function.
The red path is showing how gradient descent moves.
Ideally, gradient descent would want to just point straight at the minimum and go straight
there.
Instead, we keep finding that the gradients tend to point kind of across this canyon.
And so we keep going down the canyon wall, overshooting the bottom of the canyon, and
coming to the other side of the canyon.
So you're going this zigzagging fashion where we're always walking up or down a canyon wall
instead of kind of flowing down along the bottom of the canyon.
You can see this with neural networks.
That same paper that I mentioned earlier includes this visualization of a little 3D representation
of what happens in a neural net optimization problem with millions of parameters.
We can see that toward the end of training, gradient descent as represented by this blue
path is moving down this really tight canyon with the green 3D mesh.
And so the gradient is actually still pretty large here, but the curvature is even larger
and the curvature makes it really hard to take large steps.
Some things about this visualization are a little bit hard to understand because when
you work with multiple dimensions and project them down to just a few dimensions, some things
can be lost.
So one thing that we can't see here is that this blue curve is actually zigzagging a lot,
just like in the previous visualization.
It's just that the way that we made this plot means that we can't actually see the other
dimensions where it's zigzagging.
But those zigzags are stopping it from moving a lot faster along the bottom of this canyon.
The last topic that we'll cover for iterative optimization is the idea of constrained optimization.
But I don't actually have a lot to say about this, I'm just going to very quickly mention
a little bit about how it works.
If you have constraints for a function, like if you have some values g that measure how
much you deviate from exactly satisfying a constraint or some values h that measure how
far you are on the wrong side of some inequality, you can actually take your original function
f of x and transform it into this new function called the Lagrangian function where you penalize
the function for violating those constraints.
And you can then solve instead of just a minimization problem, you can solve a min max problem where
you want to keep increasing the coefficients on those penalty terms until you satisfy the
penalty terms.
This will give you a solution to the constrained optimization problem rather than just letting
you search over all of space.
In this book, we usually use this Lagrangian or it's also called the KKT version when
you include both the exact and the inequality constraints.
In this book, we mostly use this approach for solving problems in theory, like if we
want to show that the Gaussian is the probability distribution of the highest entropy, we can
use some of these penalty terms to constrain that the function we're searching over is
a probability distribution that's non-negative and sums to one.
In practice, if we actually want to write a program that we run where we use several
iterations to search for a solution, there's a much easier thing you can do.
Instead of having this min max problem and Lagrangian penalties and so on, you can just
project x back to the nearest point that satisfies the constraints after each step.
That's a very practical, easy to implement way of solving these kinds of problems.
Someone has asked, which data visualization did you use to plot the data points?
For that, you should read the paper.
It's a visualization that became up specifically for that paper.
It's not a standard technique.
Someone else asked, what happens if we do not choose the direction where the gradient
points, but select the direction where the step we can take is maximal?
You can actually look for directions where you intentionally seek out negative curvature
and so on.
It turns out to be difficult to do that in high-dimensional space.
Someone asks, what gradient descent optimizes would you recommend?
I would say usually Adam or gradient descent with momentum are pretty good, and a lot of
the time you should consider using gradient clipping.
The next part of our overall roadmap is to discuss what happens when we have rounding
error, when we have underflow, overflow, all of these issues that happen when we use a
finite number of bits to represent real numbers.
This is really important.
I know it sounds kind of boring to talk about this low-level stuff with bits, but writing
numerically precise code is actually a deep learning superscale.
A lot of the time you'll find that deep learning algorithms sort of work when you code them
up.
The loss will go down, the accuracy will go up, the accuracy will get within a few percentage
points of the state of the art.
You can check your code really carefully and you can find that there aren't really any
bugs, but maybe there are some things that aren't quite optimal about it.
That's often caused by a loss of numerical precision, where you run your gradient descent
algorithm and you don't get quite as good as results as you think you should.
Another time you'll find that your deep learning algorithm explodes.
You get a lot of not-in-number values.
You get a lot of very large values.
This might happen even if you make your learning rate relatively small and you think everything
should be stable.
Both of these problems actually usually come from writing code that doesn't have high enough
numerical precision.
Being able to write numerically precise code can really differentiate how well you perform
as a deep learning practitioner.
A lot of people have heard the story of how when I first thought of generative adversarial
nets, I was at a bar and I went home and I coded them up immediately.
In an hour or so later, I actually had them working.
A lot of people have wondered how I was able to do that, and part of the answer is that
I knew about all of this really boring numerical precision stuff, so I didn't waste any time
shooting myself in the foot writing numerically imprecise code.
That reduces the amount of time it takes to get the algorithm working a lot.
The basic idea is that when you use a finite number of bits to represent a real number,
you get both rounding errors and what are called truncation errors.
In a digital computer, we're usually talking about using float 32 or some other similar
schemes to represent real numbers.
That's especially true when we're using CUDA on GPUs.
Sometimes we use other floating formats.
A lot of the problems we're going to describe here will often mostly go away if you're able
to switch to float 64, but that usually requires slower computation on GPU or Maven
4C to move to CPU.
It will also force you to use more memory.
If you can write numerically precise code using float 32, then that can be a big advantage.
There's basically three categories of problems that happen on these kinds of 32-bit representations.
First, most numbers that you work with, they're not going to cause catastrophic problems on
their own, but they are going to get rounded.
If you have some real number x and you turn it into a representation on computer, it's
going to get rounded to some value x plus delta, where delta is just some small value
describing the rounding error that happened, that you'll be off by a little bit from what
you meant to be.
A larger problem is when you have some extremely large value of x, you just can't represent
it with the range of numbers that your float 32 values can represent.
It will actually get replaced by some placeholder, like inf, just saying that x is too large
to represent.
Now it's not really a finite value anymore.
You've got this infinite number, and your code will probably still go ahead and keep
doing arithmetic on this number as if it were a real value, and then you'll get in trouble.
There's another topic which is still basically a kind of rounding error, but it's a particularly
harmful kind of rounding error, where if you have a very small value of x, it can get
replaced by zero.
This is especially harmful because a lot of the algorithms in deep learning often assume
that we have some very small but non-zero variable.
For example, if you use the logistic sigmoid activation function, you can pass very negative
values to the logistic sigmoid, and algebraically, they'll never become quite zero, but in a
computer, they can definitely get rounded down to zero.
People are asking, aren't these numerical issues already addressed in the current deep
learning libraries?
The answer is basically yes, but you need to know when to look out for them.
A lot of the time, you write your own code, and you might end up rewriting a version of
something that already has a numerically stable variant.
Sometimes you might need to, for example, compute a softmax over several tensors instead
of just one tensor, and you'll need to know how to do that in a numerically stable way
if your library only provides a softmax for a single tensor.
Some other people are asking if there's any pointers on the best way to deal with NANDs.
That's basically what the next several slides will do.
Someone asks, how does the 64-bit representation solve the NAND error?
The basic idea is that if you have 32 bits, there's a certain range of values that you
can represent.
If you have 64 bits, that range expands.
So a program that might cause a NAND when you use 32 bits might actually avoid the NAND
when you use 64 bits.
If you use a program that uses even bigger numbers, you can eventually still get NANDs
for 64 bits.
It's just that fewer programs cause problems using 64 bits than using 32.
One example is, if you look at the PyLin 2 repository that I used to work on in grad
school before we had TensorFlow, you can look at some of the unit tests.
And when I compute the KL divergence between two Gaussian distributions, if I use float64,
the unit test expects the KL divergence to have a minimum value of zero.
But if I use float32, the unit test actually has to allow the KL divergence to go slightly
negative.
So one example of how we can get rounding errors and they can affect this code is what
happens when you add a very small number to a larger number.
So we're going to make an array using 32-bit floats, and we're going to store the value
zero and the value 10 to the minus eight in this array.
If we compute the argmax of this array, the argmax is one because position zero has a
value of zero, position one has a positive but very small value of 10 to the minus eight.
So now suppose that we take these numbers and we add them to a much larger number.
We add them to one.
Well, zero is going to have one added to it and end up with a value of one.
Ideally, one plus 10 to the minus eight would be represented as one, but, sorry, one, one
point, you know, zero, zero, zero, zero, zero, one after the correct number of zeros.
In this case, it's actually going to get rounded to one, which isn't quite what we want.
When you take the argmax of the new array where we added one to it, we actually get
that the argmax is zero now because NumPy breaks ties to the first index that's tied
for the max.
So this addition of a number that caused a rounding error has actually downstream changed
the results quite a lot.
We only really wanted to extract a single bit from this computation, and we're now actually
getting the value of that bit wrong.
There's some secondary effects that happen when we have rounding error and overflow and
underflow errors.
What happens is after the first error, we do some more math, and then the second error
causes a bigger problem.
So for example, say we have some code that computes x minus y.
X minus y is a relatively safe thing to do to start with.
There's definitely some ways that can go wrong, but there's not anything fundamentally wrong
with doing a subtraction.
And now suppose that x overflows to nth, y overflows to nth, well then we've got infinity
minus infinity, and we don't really know which infinity is larger.
This kind of operation is not really defined.
So now our x minus y will turn these nths into nanths.
A lot of the time when you have overflow, the way that you first see it is that you'll
get a nan in your loss function or your gradient.
So somewhere in your computational graph, you'll get an nth, and then by the time it
actually gets printed out or plotted somewhere, it will have been turned into a nan by these
additional steps of arithmetic that came afterward.
One of the main functions that's often the culprit of numerical precision problems in
deep learning programs is the x function that computes the natural logarithms base e raised
to the power of x.
This will overflow for large values of x.
And a lot of the time when I say large values, I am talking about extremely large values.
For x, when I say large values, I'm actually talking about numbers that are not very big.
If you're using float 32, a value of 89 past 2x will overflow to nth.
To make sure that your program doesn't have trouble with x, just never use large x as
the argument for x.
And make sure that you design the structure of your functions that you compute so that
they will never actually pass a large x to x.
A lot of the rest of this lecture will be about ideas for how you can prevent that from
happening in specific cases.
The other big problem with x is that if your argument to it is very negative, x of x can
underflow.
This may not be a problem.
If you think about it, x of a very negative number is just some small number epsilon.
And if you round that number down to zero, you've only made a mistake of size epsilon.
So if that was your final output of the function, it's not a very big error.
Unfortunately, if you then do other math on top of this output, rounding a small number
epsilon down to zero can be catastrophic.
If you're using x of x in a denominator or as an argument to a logarithm and so on,
it can cause really big problems.
Another case where you can sometimes encounter danger is when you have subtraction, especially
if you want to guarantee that the output of the subtraction is going to be positive.
So if you have two values, x and y, and you know algebraically that you can prove that
x is always greater than y, in a computer, you may actually find that x minus y ends
up being negative.
So if you rely on x minus y being positive in subsequent steps of your program, you
could run into trouble.
One case where we see this a lot is computing the variance.
So there's one way that you can write the variance, where it's the expectation of a
squared value.
If you implement the variance this way in your code, it's always going to give you positive
numbers because the output of the squaring value will always be non-negative.
I shouldn't say positive, sorry.
And then if you look at the difference between the expectation of the squared value of the
function and the square of the expected value of the function, algebraically that's a perfectly
valid way of rearranging this expression for the variance.
And a lot of times this is actually the one where we actually have access to those values
to compute it.
Unfortunately, it's numerically unstable because if we have a little bit of rounding error
on the left and a little bit of rounding error on the right, and these values were very close
to zero to start with, if the rounding error goes in the wrong direction, we can end up
with a small negative value instead of zero.
And that can cause trouble, especially if you were planning to pass this value to a square
root or a logarithm later on.
Logarithm and square root are also functions where you want to be very careful.
The logarithm of zero is negative infinity, and the logarithm of a negative number is
imaginary.
Usually in software frameworks like NumPy, we end up treating that as a not a number.
The square root of zero is zero, so that's actually safe, but the derivative of square
root has a divide by zero if you take the derivative at x equals zero.
So you definitely want to avoid underflow or rounding to a negative value in the argument
to either log or square root.
One very common place where this comes up is when we compute the standard deviation.
The standard deviation is the square root of the variance.
So if you compute the variance using the dangerous strategy from this slide, you can end up with
this rounding to a small negative number, and then you take the square root of that small
negative number and run into trouble.
The logarithm of x is a common pattern that comes up a lot in deep learning.
We often see this when we're computing log probabilities, and the probability is based
on taking the x of some argument.
Whenever you see this, you should simplify it to just the value x.
Theona will do this for you automatically, a lot of frameworks don't.
If you do this, you can avoid overflowing the x, because you just take x rather than
competing x of x first before competing the log.
You can also avoid underflow in x, which would then cause the logarithm to turn into negative.
So now I have a little bit of an exercise for you.
Let's say that we're doing a little bit of a hack to avoid a divide by zero.
We want to compute a normalized version of x, where x will have unit standard deviation,
and we divide x by some estimate of the standard deviation in order to do that.
We know that our standard deviation might have some round to zero troubles, so we're
going to add a small constant epsilon of 10 to the minus seven to our standard deviation
in order to make sure we don't divide by zero when we compute the normalized version of
x.
So there's two different ways we can imagine doing this.
One is we could take the square root of epsilon plus the variance, and use that as our standard
deviation.
The other version of the hack is we could take epsilon plus the square root of the variance.
So which of these is the better way to implement this hack?
Does anybody want to answer on the chat?
The first one.
So why do you say the first one?
Oh, you got to vote for the second one as well.
So does somebody want to give a reason for one of their votes?
So the square root of x will be too small.
That can definitely happen.
If your x is already just barely as big as you can represent and variance is zero, it
can round down.
There's also another issue here, which is think about what happens if the variance is
already implemented safely, and we know that it won't get rounded down too low.
Let's also suppose we make epsilon a little bit bigger, so if we divide by a square root
of epsilon, that won't give us divide by zero.
Is there any other problem that might come up here?
So there is one other problem that might come up here.
If we use this version, where we have the epsilon plus square root of the variance, we
can actually get, when we compute the derivative of normalized x later on, we can have this
problem that the square root of the variance might be evaluated exactly for the variance
being equal to zero, and when we take the derivative of square root, we actually get
a divide by zero in that case.
So usually you want to put the epsilon inside the square root, but you do need to make sure
that your epsilon is big enough that it won't get rounded down to zero when you take the
square root.
Another function that comes up all the time in deep learning is log sum x.
You see this in things like the cross entropy function.
The naive way of implementing this is if you have an array, you apply x to the array, then
you sum out the x values, and then you take the log at the end.
The failure modes to this are those two different ways that can go wrong.
One is if any of your entries in the array is big, your x can overflow.
So you just take x of some large number in float 32, a value of 90 would do this to you.
You overflow.
Now you've got an inf here.
When you start doing arithmetic on the inf, it's probably going to turn into a noun pretty
soon.
That one's relatively obvious.
A lot of people realize that that one's going to happen.
Another case that this can fail is if all of the entries in the array are very negative,
then all of the x's underflow to zero.
Individually, each of these mistakes in the x is not a big deal.
X of a very negative number is some small number epsilon.
You round that to zero, your error is only order of epsilon.
The problem is when you sum up all the zeros, if all of them are literally zero, then the
sum is also literally zero.
And then you pass that to a log.
So you get a negative int at the end, even if that's not algebraically the correct answer.
So the good news is there's a relatively simple trick that lets us fix this.
The way it works is we take the maximum of the array, and then we subtract the maximum
off all of the entries.
Then we compute log sum x of this new safe array that had the max subtracted off of it.
And we add the max back on to the result after we take the log.
In TensorFlow, there's a build-in version that does this for you, tf.reduce log sum
x.
You do need to know to use that, though.
Someone was saying, don't all the deep learning frameworks already solve this?
Well, a lot of them provide solutions to it, but you have to know to use those solutions.
So whenever you see yourself doing a log sum x, be sure to use the stable variant of
it.
If we look at why this works, first off, we need to make sure that we're actually computing
the value that we want.
We want to see that the new expression is algebraically equivalent to the old one.
So the way that we can see this is we've got this variable m representing the max.
We've got this vector a representing the array.
The new value that we're computing is m plus log sum over i of x of ai minus m.
Well, each of these x terms, we can use the fact that x of ai minus m turns into x of
ai divided by x of m.
And so we've simplified these terms inside the sum.
Now it turns out that every term in the sum has this factor division by x of m, and this
factor doesn't depend on ai at all.
So we can actually pull it outside the summation.
So now we've got this 1 over x m factor multiplied by this summation factor.
Well, a logarithm of two factors can be split into the sum of the logarithm of both those
factors.
The logarithm of 1 over x is actually just negative log of x.
We get m minus log x m plus the sum over all these factors.
This log x, obviously, that turns into the identity.
So we get m minus m, this cancels, and oh, I actually have a mistake.
I left out the log here, but there should be a log right there.
So we've actually recovered the original version of the expression that we were trying to optimize.
So the other thing we need to check to see that this works is we need to make sure that
the two failure modes we identified earlier are gone.
So we notice that there is a way that we can overflow the original version.
We've also noticed that there was a way we could underflow every term of the original
version and then get a negative int when we pass it to the log.
So first let's look at the overflow case.
Because we subtract off the max, all of the entries of safe array are at most zero.
X of zero is just one, so we can compute that without any overflow.
So we've eliminated the overflow problem.
There was the case where every value of the x underflows.
Well, we can still have a problem where some of the x terms underflow.
The good news is subtracting off the max actually means that there has to be at least one entry
of safe array that's equal to zero.
Any entries that were tied for the max now have a value of zero.
And so those are not going to underflow when we take the x.
They'll get a value of one, and that's a nice stable value that can be computed easily.
That means that the sum is now at least one, and we can safely pass that sum to the logarithm.
So someone is asking if there's any book or blog summarizing all these numerical computation
problems in the context of deep learning.
There are definitely books about numerical computation.
A lot of them don't really focus specifically on the problems that come up a lot in deep learning.
And I don't actually know of one that is focused in that way.
I will probably write an article about it or add it to the second edition of the deep
learning textbook.
But I don't know of a good resource to point you to yet other than this lecture.
The softmax function comes up all the time in deep learning.
We use it as the output of most neural nets for classification, for generating text, for
selecting discrete actions in reinforcement learning agents.
The main advice for the softmax is that you should use your library's buildinsoftmax function.
If you try to make your own, it's easy to mess up and get a numerically unstable version.
If you do build your own, the way that you should do it is you should take the argument
to the softmax, the logits, and you should track off the maximum value before you pass
it through the softmax.
The reason this works is very similar to the log sum x.
I won't walk through exactly what all of the justification for it is, but it's basically
the same logic as what we just saw with log sum x.
The sigmoid function is also very common in deep learning.
And it's essentially the same thing as softmax.
It's basically a softmax where one of the inputs is hard coded to zero, and you pass
it out just one of the outputs.
So once again, the recommendation is to use your library's buildin sigmoid function.
If you don't, you can stabilize it using the same trick as with the softmax.
The cross entropy function is the loss for most neural nets that we train, especially
if you have a softmax output.
Everything that I say here also applies with sigmoid.
Just replace the word softmax with sigmoid.
This is probably one of the most common things that I see people screw up in deep learning
is they implement their own cross entropy function, and they compute it using the probabilities.
They actually literally apply the softmax and then compute the loss.
What you actually want to do is use the logits, the values output by the neural net before
you get to the softmax.
And you want to compute your loss in terms of those.
The reason is that the probabilities will lose gradient when the softmax saturates.
The cross entropy function won't saturate unless you're already getting the right answer,
and then you don't need any gradient because you're already winning.
The short recommendation for how to write good code is to use a numerically stable version
of the cross entropy function that's already provided to you by your library.
If you're using TensorFlow, you can use tf.nn.softmax cross entropy with logits.
If you're using another software framework, you need to be very careful and check that
it actually is computing the cross entropy using the logits rather than the probabilities.
A lot of frameworks screw this up and use the output of the softmax rather than the
input to the softmax.
It's a common enough problem that I've actually seen this in frameworks that I've used.
If you do make your own cross entropy function, you should use the stabilization tricks for
the softmax and the log sum x that come up inside this loss function in order to stabilize
it.
In general, if you have some bugs that you're encountering, there are a few really simple
strategies that you can follow to catch them.
One thing is that if you increase the learning rate for your gradient descent algorithm and
the loss function value gets stuck, that for a very large learning rate, you find that
your loss is flat over time as you take more steps.
That probably means that the gradient is getting routed down to zero somewhere in your graph.
You probably are losing numerical precision and ending up without a gradient.
Otherwise, a large learning rate should make you move faster and faster and actually cause
explosion rather than getting stuck.
The most common way that I've seen this happen is when the cross entropy loss is calculated
using probabilities instead of logits.
If the softmax rounds a probability to one or zero, then the gradient through it is gone
and you can't do very much about it.
A lot of the time, people that encounter this problem with extreme values of the softmax
will hack around it by clipping the value of the softmax somehow or other to avoid extreme
values.
That will make sure that you don't get nons in the forward prop when you take a log of
the softmax, but it will also mean that you get zeros in the back prop when you try to
compute the gradients.
That's a really common bug.
It's pretty easy to identify by the learning curve being flat.
I've actually seen this a lot in third-party open-source implementations of generative
adversarial nodes.
This is one of those cases where it will look like you don't have a bug because if you use
a small enough learning rate, your code will basically work, but it just won't perform
quite as well as it ought to.
If you use a large learning rate, then it will break and it will look like the algorithm
is not robust to hyperparameters, but really the problem is that your code is not numerically
precise enough to handle some of the larger learning rates.
Another one of the bug hunting strategies I use is just if you see an explosion, immediately
become very suspicious of anywhere that you see a log x square root or division in your
code and just look and see if you're doing a divide by zero, a square root of a negative
number and x of a large number and so on.
Also, you should always suspect the code that has changed the most recently.
For example, if you were running your code and everything's fine and then eventually
you add something like batch norm and suddenly you see explosion, then you should probably
suspect that maybe the problem is when you divide by the square root of the variance
in your batch norm, and that's very likely to be where the problem is.
A lot of the time I find that when I'm helping people like interns or brain residents, just
following this bug hunting strategy with my colleagues at Google Brain will help me almost
immediately solve problems that were very mysterious for someone who is new to deep learning.
And if you can learn this pattern, it can accelerate your workflow quite a lot.
Okay, thanks.
Glad you enjoyed the talk.